Guide to the International Congress on the Enlightenment Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
International Congress on the Enlightenment, records
1967-1976
RU 194
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10.75
The records consist of the administrative files of Georges May, secretary of the International Congress on the Enlightenment, which held its fourth meeting at Yale University in 1975. Records concerning earlier congresses are also included.
International Congress on the Enlightenment
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 50 (YRG 50), Records of conferences and symposia at Yale.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of the administrative files of Georges May, secretary of the International Congress on the Enlightenment, which held its fourth meeting at Yale University in 1975. Records concerning earlier congresses are also included.
The Fourth International Congress on the Enlightenment held July 12-20, 1975, at Yale University culminated years of preparation by The Congress Secretariat headed by Georges May. The papers consist of pre-registration correspondence with participants, organizational files of the coordinators of the Congress, and printed matter. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent, the pre-registration correspondence includes letters of inquiry, registration forms, and drafts of scholarly papers to be presented. The organizational files contain correspondence and memoranda between the coordinators of the Congress on the one hand, and Yale University and New Haven officials and services on the other. The papers also contain circulars, newsletters, menus, and programs of events held during the Congress. Included in Box 17 is a list said to contain the names of all those who participated in the Congress or who corresponded with the Congress Secretariat and did not attend. However, there are many scholars unaccounted for, who either are not listed and had correspondence wfth the Congress, or who had correspondence and did not attend. One must therefore look at both the correspondence and the list to get a complete view of the Congress.
In March of 1978 an addition to the papers of the Fourth International Congress on the Enlightenment was sent to Yale University Archives. It contains papers on previous congresses, the pre-conference work of the program committee, registration sheets for participants, press coverage, and financial papers. Covering the period from 1967-76, this addition is in boxes 18-26 of the collection.
Congresses and conventions; Enlightenment -- Congresses; Meetings; May, Georges, 1920-; International Congress on the Enlightenment
- Records, 1967-1976; Accession 19ND-A-230
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - Participant Correspondence, 1972-1975
    - Aa - Be (Box 1)
    - Bi - Ca (Box 2)
    - Ch - De (Box 3)
    - Di - Ff (Box 4)
    - Fi - Go (Box 5)
    - H - He (Box 6)
    - Hi - Ka (Box 7)
    - Ke - Le (Box 8)
    - Li - Ma (Box 9)
    - Me - Pa (Box 10)
    - Pe - Ra (Box 11)
    - Re - Sc (Box 12)
    - Se - Sw (Box 13)
    - T - Vo (Box 14)
    - W - Z (Box 15)
  - Organizational Correspondence, 1969-1975
    - A - Bs C - Yale, L (Box 16)
    - Yale, M - W (Box 17)
  - Circulars, programs, menus, newsletters, mailing list of Enlightenment Congress participants, 1973-1975 (Box 17)
  - Second Enlightenment Congress of St. Andrew's, 1967 August (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Correspondents du Congres des Lumieres, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Enlightenment Congress questionnaire, Nancy, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Questionnaires filled out at the 3rd Congress at Nancy re 4th Congress, A - R, 1971 (Box 18, Folder 5-18)
  - Questionnaires filled out at the 3rd Congress at Nancy re 4th Congress, S - Z, 1971 (Box 19, Folder 19-21)
  - Liste alphabetique des participants aux trois prdedents congres (Box 19, Folder 22)
  - Interim Planning Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 19, Folder 23)
  - Program committee, 1973-1975 (Box 19, Folder 24-26)
  - 4th Congress: notes and comments, 1973-1975 (Box 19, Folder 27)
  - First Circular, 1972-1973 (Box 19, Folder 28-30)
  - Second Circular, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 31-33)
  - Third Circular, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 34-36)
  - Summaries of proposed papers (Box 20, Folder 37)
  - Propositions de communications en suspens, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 38)
  - Scheduling requests (Box 20, Folder 39)
  - Final report and relevant correspondence, 1975-1976 (Box 20, Folder 40)
  - Programs, menus, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 41)
  - Lunch parties during congress, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 42)
  - GAZETTE duCpmgres, 1975 July 14-19 (Box 20, Folder 43)
  - Rameau's Nephew by Denis Diderot, translated by Michael Feingold (Box 20, Folder 44)
  - Student aids (Box 20, Folder 45)
  - Final list of Congress participants and correspondents, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 46)
  - Registration sheets A - Z, 1975 (Box 21, Folder 47-70)
  - re: Housing of participants, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 71-74)
  - New registrants, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 75)
  - Delegates who paid and did not attend, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 76)
  - Did not attend (Box 22, Folder 77)
  - Nouvelles inscriptions a partir du 11 juillet, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 78)
  - Deletions, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 79)
  - Lists of participants, 1975 (Box 22, Folder 80)
  - Press coverage, 1975 (Box 23, Folder 81-90)
  - Financial records (Box 24, Folder 91)
    - Accounting miscellaneous, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 91)
    - American Council of Learned Societies (ACLS), 1971-1976 (Box 24, Folder 92-93)
    - American Revolution Bicentennial Commission, 1971-1975 (Box 24, Folder 94)
    - Board and room account, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 95)
    - Casual employment, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 96)
    - Comptroller' s Office, 1973 (Box 24, Folder 97)
    - Congress guest expenses, 1975 (Box 24, Folder 98)
    - Equipment and supplf es, 1973-1975 (Box 24, Folder 99-100)
    - Form, 1975-1976 (Box 24, Folder 101-102)
    - International Association for Federal Union (IAFU), 1974 (Box 24, Folder 104)
    - International Research and Exchange Board (IREX), 1974-1975 (Box 25, Folder 105-106)
    - Musical events account, 1975 (Box 25, Folder 110)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), 1970-1976 (Box 25, Folder 111-115)
    - Office staff, 1972-1975 (Box 25, Folder 116)
    - Sheraton-Park Plaza Hotel, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 118)
    - Special use account, 1971-1975 (Box 26, Folder 119)
    - Subsidf es awarded, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 120)
    - Telephone, 1973-1975 (Box 26, Folder 121)
    - Transactions account, 1975-1976 (Box 26, Folder 122)
    - Travel grant applications, 1975 (Box 26, Folder 123)
    - UNESCO, 1971-1974 (Box 26, Folder 124)
    - Yale dining halls and rooms, 1972-1975 (Box 26, Folder 126)
    - Yale Station: Cerrone, Frank L, 1973-1974 (Box 26, Folder 127)